<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The counter buffe or, Certaine observations upon Mr. Edvvards his animadversions, touching a pamphlet intituled Little Non-such whereby is discernd how passion or spleene may transport some that would be thought great clerks which according to the proverb, doth not alwayes prove the wisest men.  To avoyd all partiality, we will first lay downe Mr. Edwards his own words, touching the three heads he hath culd out of the aforesaid pamphlet, and then our observations upon each shewing (in conclusion) how much hee mistakes the right Independent. If thy minde be busied elsewhere, lay this booke aside till better leysure, it will require privacy and thy best attention.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80672</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872692</idno>
  <idno type="VID">160389</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240939644</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E399_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4500</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872692</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99872692e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80672)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E399[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The counter buffe or, Certaine observations upon Mr. Edvvards his animadversions, touching a pamphlet intituled Little Non-such whereby is discernd how passion or spleene may transport some that would be thought great clerks which according to the proverb, doth not alwayes prove the wisest men.  To avoyd all partiality, we will first lay downe Mr. Edwards his own words, touching the three heads he hath culd out of the aforesaid pamphlet, and then our observations upon each shewing (in conclusion) how much hee mistakes the right Independent. If thy minde be busied elsewhere, lay this booke aside till better leysure, it will require privacy and thy best attention.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed as formerly, for H.P.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 22th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Little Non-such.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Independent churches --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian sects --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160389:1"/>
            <p>THE COUNTER BVFFE OR, CERTAINE OBSERVATIONS upon Mr. EDVVARDs his <hi>Animadversions,</hi> touching a Pamphlet intituled little <hi>Non-such,</hi> Whereby is discernd how passion or spleene may transport some that would be thought great Clerks which according to the Proverb, doth not alwayes prove the wisest Men.</p>
            <p>To avoyd all partiality, we will first lay downe Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his own words, touching the three Heads he hath culd out of the aforesaid Pamphlet, and then our Observation upon each Shewing (in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion) how much hee mistakes the Right Independent.</p>
            <p>If thy minde be busied elsewhere, lay this Booke aside till better leysure, it will require privacy and thy best Attention.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Non est bonum Ludere cum Sanctis.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed as formerly, for <hi>H. P.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:160389:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:160389:2"/>
            <div type="text">
               <head>THE FIRST HEAD OF Mr. Edwards, <hi>LITTLE NON-SƲCH.</hi> PAGE 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat God hath a bodily shape and proportion, Men was made according to the likenesse of God in personall shape, And God the Creator beareth the same shape in person which Man hath: This opinion was held by some <hi>Hereticks</hi> in the fourth <hi>Century</hi> first known by the name of <hi>Audiani,</hi> and afterwards call'd <hi>Anthrop<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>morph<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ae. August.</hi> in his book <hi>de Heresibus ad qu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d vuit deum</hi> cap <hi>50.</hi> Writes of them. Audianos <hi>quos apellant alii vocant Anthropomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itas quoniam Deum, fibi fingunt cogitatione c<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li in Similitudinem Imaginis corruptilibis hominis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <head>Animadversion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> in his fourth Booke <hi>de He<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erib. fabuli,</hi> Writes there was one <hi>Audeus</hi> who said God was like to man and gave to G<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the parts of a man, who fell into this error by his misunderstanding of those places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> which speake of God according to mans understanding:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:160389:3"/>
                  <hi>Danaeus</hi> in his <hi>Tractate</hi> de <hi>Heresibus</hi> fully confutes this opinion, and shewes the story of it; and that this <hi>Heresy</hi> should be now pleaded for in Print, it shewes how the Devill in these times revives old errors dead and buried for many hundred yeares.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="observation">
               <head>The first Observation.</head>
               <p>First, we give you to understand that the Contents of little <hi>Non-such</hi> are certaine Questions moved to be resolved in (under correction) as appeares in the preamble, and not positively maintain'd as mattrr of faith, as doth also appeare <hi>page</hi> 16. Therefore Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath falsify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the first Head, speaking his own words but not the <hi>Authors,</hi> nor yet their intentions: then all hee sayth to the matter is, that there were certaine <hi>Hereticks</hi> in the fourth <hi>Century</hi> cal'd <hi>Audiani</hi> &amp; <hi>Anthropomorphitoe</hi> which maintained the opinion aforesaid. And how <hi>Augustin</hi> sayd they were so call'd, because they feigned unto themselves that God had a shape like unto corruptable man: and how then did they say that was a corruptable shape?<note place="margin">☞</note> hee saith also that <hi>Danaeus</hi> in his <hi>Tractate</hi> confuted them, but hee neither shewes how, nor by what proofe of <hi>Scripture</hi> as is desired; so that the ignorant are nothing the more satisfyed by Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> his Doctrine: then he seems to wounder how this <hi>Heresy,</hi> as he calls it, should be pleaded for in Print; we would here know of any reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able man if the bare asking of a question be pleading for an <hi>Heresy;</hi> if this be faire play what call you <hi>Legerdemaine?</hi> Th re are yet more places in <hi>Scripture</hi> then are layd downe in little <hi>Non-such,</hi> which may move a man to aske such a question as that of <hi>Gen.</hi> 35 <hi>v.</hi> 9. Where God appeared unto <hi>Jacob,</hi> and then ascended from him in the place where he had tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with him, verse 13. this may imply some shape, else how did God appeare to him and ascend from him; then in the seventh of <hi>Daniel</hi> v. 9. Doth not the ancient of dayes sitting in a Robe with haire of h s head as white as Wooll imply a shape also; yet notwithstanding these or any other Reasons out of <hi>Scripture</hi> and cited in Little <hi>Non-such,</hi> what ever the forenamed <hi>Hereticks</hi> thought wee assure Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> that wee doe not make it our Creede, or thinke it any point of salvation to beleive so, well knowing (as is set forth in Little <hi>Non such</hi>) that God is omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, and that his power cannot be circumscribed in any personall shape or place; for wee can cite St. <hi>Augustin</hi> as well as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> and give him credit too, when hee saith cursed is hee that refer<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the <hi>Deity</hi> of God to the liniaments of mans body, for that were a narrow <hi>Deity,</hi> and we suppose no <hi>Heretick</hi> can be so grosse as to conclude in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; yet that each of the three persons have assumed shapes is confessed by learned men, but for what purpose or of what continuance they were or shall be, or what is the meaning of the words let us make man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our own <hi>Image,</hi> seeing the first man <hi>Adam</hi> was an <hi>Image</hi> of clay made in the six Dayes, but was not a living <hi>soule</hi> till God had rested the seaventh Day, and then breath'd life into him; These thing we would
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:160389:3"/> have learn'd from Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> by some reasons backe with <hi>Scripture</hi> proofe, but hee hath onely corrup ed the meaning of the question, and told a tale of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> so that our selves nor we suppose any other (by his <hi>Animadversion,</hi> is any thing at all the wiser.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>The next Head is little <hi>Non-such,</hi> Page <hi>4.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> The story of <hi>Adams</hi> eating the forbidden fruit and of the Serpent is an <hi>Allegory,</hi> by the <hi>Serpent</hi> in that place is meant no other then <hi>concupisence,</hi> and by the fruit of the Tree, some other eating then the eating of a <hi>materiall Apple,</hi> is derstood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <head>Animadversion.</head>
               <p>This also is an error revived, held by <hi>David George,</hi> who lived a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares ago; in <hi>David Georges</hi> life written in Latin by his Son in Law <hi>Nicholus Blesdikins</hi> page 161. 162. 'tis related that by the <hi>Serpent</hi> entising our first parents, he meant <hi>concupisence,</hi> and pleades for an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legoricall</hi> interpretation of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> because the Historicall narration of the <hi>Serpent</hi> as it is layd down by <hi>Moses</hi> (sayth <hi>David George</hi>) drawes divers absurdities with it: the marginall Note here saith also that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> among other errors of the <hi>Originists</hi> shewes this to bee one, and how St. <hi>Augustin</hi> writ many Bookes against <hi>Alegorists</hi> and corrupters of Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>The second Observation.</head>
               <p>Now if you mark how Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath layd down this second Head (instead of giving inst uction) you will perceive how willing he is to pick a quarrell, for this is but a questi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in little <hi>Non such</hi> (as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) and demanded with all modesty, peruse it who please, but setting aside his spleene, let us examine his <hi>Animadversion,</hi> and see what satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction it gives, which saith no more you see, but that it is an error re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, held by one <hi>David George</hi> as appeares in his life written by his son in Law <hi>Nicolaus Blesdikins,</hi> and then how <hi>Danaeus</hi> shewes it to be an error of the <hi>Originists,</hi> how if <hi>Origen</hi> had sayd as much of him? and then he saith in the margent how <hi>Augustin</hi> writ against <hi>Allegorists</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupters of Scripture: what thinke you of this solution?<note place="margin">☜</note> is this a satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory answer to the question in little <hi>Non such?</hi> where is his Texts in <hi>Scripture</hi> to reconcile those that are cited there, if the meaning be otherwise: what would hee make us believe there are no <hi>allegories</hi> in <hi>Scripture?</hi> we are not so simple to credit him in that point; wee know there are both <hi>Allegories, Tropes,</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> what admirable expressions is there in the Book of <hi>Job?</hi> what <hi>Metaphors</hi> and <hi>Retoricall Figures?</hi> and as one saith the <hi>Retorick</hi> of <hi>Cicero, Demosthenes, Hortensius,</hi> &amp;c. is but a shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow in comparison; and in another place the same Author sayth the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation is full of <hi>mysterious metaphoricall</hi> and <hi>Hiereogliphicall Charecters;</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:160389:4"/> And if Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> would have us understand our Saviours words this is my body to be h s Body, then we say Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> is <hi>pop<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sh: Turtullian</hi> say<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, it is but a F<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gure of his Body: And did not our <hi>Saviour</hi> in the <hi>Gosp ll</hi> deliver his Doctrine in <hi>Parables,</hi> and darke speeches, insomuch as the Apostles themselves sayd, Master what is the meaning, observe here the <hi>Discipl<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> did not thinke it <hi>Heresy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> to aske a question as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> doth: it is the manner of such as are able and willing to resolve doubts to compare one place of <hi>Scrip<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ure</hi> with another, and then to give us a right interpretation, if Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> had done so here wee would have thank'd him: concerning this portion of <hi>Scripture</hi> (if sufficeth us to know there was a breach of a Commandement in our first Parents, which hath inthral'd us in <hi>Originall sin,</hi> but whether the words be <hi>allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall</hi> or <hi>literall</hi> (thou<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h we would willingly have knowne something of which M. <hi>Edwards</hi> (it seemes is ignorantly silent) yet we say of this as the former, we make it no point of faith as touching our salvation: But for the third, and next in order, we verily believe it is as grose a peece of <hi>popery</hi> as is, or ever was since that wyly Father was rightly stiled an usurper.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <head>The third Head is little <hi>Non-such,</hi> Page <hi>5, 6, 7.</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> in Marriage there are no degrees of bloud or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity forbidden, but a man may marry the next of kin to him, a Brother may marry his Sister, his Ʋncle his Neece, a Son his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers VVife, and so in any degrees without exception; so that if this liking to marry happen betwixt the nearest of Kindred, then it is also the most naturall, the most lawfull, and according to the <hi>Primitive</hi> purity and practise.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="animadversion">
               <head>Animadversion.</head>
               <p>The maine scope of this Book call'd little <hi>Non-such,</hi> or certaine new Questions is to plead for <hi>incestuous Marriages,</hi> where the Author sets himselfe to evade all the <hi>Scriptures</hi> in the old and new <hi>Testament,</hi> saying it is not Marriage simply with Sisters Brothers wives, &amp;c. that is forb d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den so long as a man keepes wholy to such a one, having taken her for a Wife, but the committing fornication with them not being Married: Now I shall shew the falsnesse of this by two <hi>Scriptures,</hi> the first in <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. where both in the Generall <hi>v.</hi> 6. and in particular the severall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees are expresly forbidden <hi>v.</hi> 7 8, 9, 10, &amp;c. of the Fathers Wife of the Sister, of the fathers sister, &amp;c. And whereas the Author of that wicked Pamphlet pleads that uncovering of nakednesse is meant of fornication only and not of Marriage. I answer the holy Ghost in that Chapter expounds the uncovering of nakednesse to be<note n="a" place="margin">A flat untruth.</note> Marrying, <hi>v.</hi> 18. and makes the taking to w<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe and uncovering of nakednesse to be the same as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently by these words, neither shalt thou take a Wife to her sister to vex
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:160389:4"/> her, to uncover her nakednesse besides the other in her life time, that is either thou shalt not take one Wife to another marrying another Wife having one or else marry the sister of thy Wife, whether shee be sister by father or by mother. Againe the holy Ghost in this Chapter forbids that which is is unlawfull with some kinde of persons, and not with all<note n="b" place="margin">How prove you that?</note> and at some time, and not at others; Therefore limits to such a sort of persons, such degrees of bloud: but now fornication is unlawfull with all and at all times: A man may not uncover the nakednesse, that is, to commit<note n="c" place="margin">Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe.</note> fornication with those that are remotest in bloud or Affinity, and that it must be understood so, is evident from the 19 <hi>verse,</hi> thou shalt not approach to a woman to uncover her nakednesse, so long as she is put apart for her uncleannesse, that is every man was to abstaine from his owne Wife during the time of her Monethly flowers, which necessarily shewes is meant of a mans Wife, for from all other Women a Man must abstaine alwayes, and it is never lawfull to approach to them, but even from a mans owne Wife over whose body he hath power at other times, hee is then to abstaine: Lastly, the Holy <hi>Ghost</hi> comes to speake of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <hi>vers.</hi> 20. Thou shall not lie carnally with thy Neighbours Wife, there he forbibs fornication, but in the former part of the Chapter he forbad <hi>incest</hi> and <hi>incestuous</hi> Marriages:<note n="d" place="margin">If all be true that you say.</note> The other Scripture is in the new <hi>Testament</hi> marke the 6.17, 18. <hi>verses,</hi> where <hi>Iohn</hi> tells <hi>Herod</hi> it is not lawfull for him to have his brother <hi>Phillips</hi> Wife, and this cannot be eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by saying, <hi>Iohn</hi> reproved <hi>Herod</hi> for taking her by force or living in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, but not barely for Marriage with her: for the Text saith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly he had married her, and she was willing to it as appeares by the story, because she had a quarrell against <hi>John Baptist,</hi> and would have kil'd him for preaching to <hi>Herod</hi> against it, and afterwards watch'd her op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of revenge against <hi>John v.</hi> 19.24. prefering his head before half the Kingdome; I have beene the larger in this <hi>Animadversion,</hi> because of divers <hi>s<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctuaries</hi> and <hi>incestuous</hi> Marriages: I have the names of three <hi>Independents</hi> (given me out of one County) who have married <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestuously.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observation">
               <head>The third Observation.</head>
               <p>This head because M <hi>Edwards</hi> will keepe his rode, hee makes positive also, wheras it is but a question as the two former; <hi>Tene per asinum,</hi> which at Bowles is as much to say as hold <hi>Bias:</hi> Then he sayeth the <hi>Authour</hi> sets himselfe to evade <hi>Scriptures,</hi> no indeed M. <hi>Edwards;</hi> but except there be mo e convincing reasons then you have showne, the <hi>Authors</hi> intent was, and is to prove by <hi>Scripture,</hi> that the prohibition mentioned is a <hi>popish</hi> injunction, not rightly grounded out of <hi>Scripture:</hi> They say also it is a sencelesse Prohibition, for as touching matters forbid in the <hi>Decalogue</hi> which is the ground of all Lawes, they are obnoxious in themselves (if there were no such injunction) both to the parties offending and unto them to whom the offence is given: but in the most affectionate mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:160389:5"/> there is the most and greatest good to both parties, which the <hi>pope</hi> nor perhaps M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> would admit with out a fee: The first head Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> taxes as an <hi>Heresy</hi> though it is but a question asked: The second Question he calls an error, but for this third we are so much beholding unto him as hee calls it neither Heresy nor error; yet in one place hee is pleased to say it is a wicked Pamphlet, this is hard too, for if one should aske M. <hi>Edwards</hi> the way to <hi>York</hi> or to <hi>Bristow;</hi> would hee say thou art a vile and a wicked fellow, thou shalt fall in the ditch before I will direct thee, is this charity to a stranger that is astray, what thinke you? now M <hi>Edwards</hi> if men shall fall from an error into flat <hi>Heresy,</hi> yet St. <hi>Jerome</hi> tells us in <hi>paeni lib.</hi> 4. in <hi>Jeremia,</hi> it is to bee cut of with the sword of the spirit, that is with the Testimonies of Holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> let us strike through with the arrowes of the spirit and not by reviling and execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but it seemes it is M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his manner to bee bitter, and to administer Gall instead of Honey, for wee have seene a little <hi>Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> that (for his invectivenes) calls him <hi>Thomas</hi> de <hi>Gangrena,</hi> which made us take him for a <hi>Monsieur,</hi> till a little after it sayes hee is one of <hi>Rabsh<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kaghs</hi> Champions; well then if hee bee a Champion hee may perhaps when a place is voyd, bee one of the nine Worthies; but doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse hee will never be one of the seven Wise Masters, till hee leave his reviling and give us instruction in the spirit of meekenesse.</p>
               <p>And now though hee passe by the two former Questions without citing any <hi>Scripture,</hi> yet because hee tells us hee wlll shew the false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of this question by two <hi>Scriptures,</hi> let him bee what Champion hee will, wee will here enter the lists with him, and hope to foyle him at his owne Weapon, two <hi>Scriptures</hi> you heare him say, but if hee could have showne the falsenesse (as wee have done the truth in the first part) by 22 <hi>Scriptures</hi> you should then have heard his great Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracke; well you see what flourish they have made at the first onset, yet now you shall see these two, as well as the rest, foigne against him and turne the point in his owne bosome.</p>
               <p>The first <hi>Scripture</hi> hee cites is the 6, 7, 8, 9, and tenth Verses of the 18 Chapter of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> which who so please to reade shall finde they speake plainly of uncovering of nakednesse, and some Translations renders it uncovering of shame; new wee never heard it was a shame to Marry or a shame to performe the Act of Marriage, but rather a duty commanded; Therefore (by his leave, wee yet conceive the interpretation of these Verses in Little <hi>Non-such</hi> to bee right, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstands them of the highest degree of fornication being committed with Kindred; And doth in the whole progresse of that discourse de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test it as much as M. <hi>Edwards</hi> can doe or any other, Then hee sayth (if wee believe him) hee will prove uncovering of nakednesse and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying to be all one by the 18 Verse, and cites these words neither shalt thou take a Wife to her sister to vex her, to uncover her nakednesse, besides the other in her life time: Doubt lesse this is foule play and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:160389:5"/> much detested in Little <hi>Non-such,</hi> where it speakes against plurality of Wives at one time: for if a Man having married a Wife and while shee is living, take her sister to uncover her nakednesse, it is fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the highest degree, and wee say no other, but if the first Wife bee dead, then the same words seeme to imply, that hee may safely marry the other, else what neede these words <hi>in her life time</hi> for from thence wee argue <hi>contrario,</hi> that when shee is dead, her Husband cannot vex her by taking her sister to Wife, as it would have done when shee was living, and it is no more but convertible with the Brothers case in <hi>Deutronomy</hi> if the first sister die without issue: Though the <hi>Patriark Jacob</hi> married two naturall sisters being both living, which some say prefigures the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Gospell</hi> unto us, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Leah</hi> (who was blear eyed, the Law is denoted unto us; and by <hi>Rachel</hi> (who was comly as the Spouse in the <hi>Canticles</hi> and without blemish) is meant the <hi>Gospell;</hi> yet seeing our <hi>Saviour</hi> sayes, let every one have his owne Wife in the singular number, so farre wee agree with M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> if he please, that no man ought to have two Wives living at one time, but how he proves by this 18. vers. that the precedent part of this Chapter is meant of Marriage, we doe not yet understand, but doe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beleive by this 18. v. to prove directly the contrary: And now we call not for such as will prejudicate or are selfe conceipted for want of wit and judgement, but to those that are apprehensive,<note place="margin">☜</note> and able to poyse the weight of this argument: This 18. v. alleadged for his proofe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins with these words, <hi>neither</hi> shalt thou &amp;c. some translations have it <hi>also</hi> and some <hi>moreover,</hi> it skills not much which of the three we admit of: for where the words neither, also, or moreover begins a sentence, it likewise imports a new matter; then observe the precedent part of this Chapter, till you come to this 18. vers. now in question; the 6. v. saith none of you shall approach to any that is neere of kin to uncover their <hi>nakednesse,</hi> or their <hi>shame</hi> as some translations have it: the rest of the verses following till you come to the 18. v. speakes one continued phrase, <hi>viz.</hi> thou shalt not uncover, thou shalt not uncover such and such, &amp;c. but at the 18. v. comes in the words <hi>neither</hi> shalt thou take a wife to her Sister to vex her in her life time, &amp;c. the 19. v. begins with <hi>also,</hi> the 20. v with <hi>moreover,</hi> being all distinct matter from the former part of the Chapter. Therefore under favour, the 18. vers. serves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Edwards</hi> no more then the 19, 20. or the rest of the verses follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which are all of different and contrary matter; for we hope hee will not say that lying carnally with another mans wife or with man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, &amp;c. hath any relation to <hi>marriage:</hi> Then we will here give you our sense of this Chapter as we conceive it now, and must doe till some other hath opened the meaning better then Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath done, <hi>viz.</hi> by the first part of the Chapter unto the 18. v. (and by the words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering shame or nakednesse) we are most especially, forbid to make
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:160389:6"/>
                  <hi>concubines,</hi> or commit fornication with any of our kindred, for though it might be unlawfull to doe it with any, yet you see the custome was amongst the <hi>Patriarks,</hi> and long time after in <hi>Davids</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> time to have many wives and <hi>Concubines,</hi> and though we ought not to injure any, yet least of all ought we to abuse our kindred, and for proofe of this we once more instance the 16. v. which saith thou shalt uncover not the <hi>nakednesse</hi> of thy brothers wife; but in <hi>Deutromy</hi> 'tis said, thou shalt <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> thy brothers wife;<note place="margin">☞</note> therefore we cannot say that uncovering naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and marrying is all one, as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> doth, but verily thinke they differ as much in sense, as lawfull and unlawfull; for if these two places have one meaning, they make the holy Spirit contradict it selfe, which to say were no lesse then <hi>blasphemy;</hi> therefore we must needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his construction in this point, and thus farre as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fornication with kindred: next we come to the 18. v. it selfe, cited by Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> to a wrong purpose; for therein we say begins a new matter; the former part of the Chapter forbids fornication with kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; in this verse we are forbid to have plurality of wives living at one time; by the 19. v. we are to avoid the uncleanesse of <hi>menses preflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> to speake more mannerly then Mr: <hi>Edwards</hi> doth, by the 20 vers. we are forbid Adultery with our neighbours wife: the 21. forbids the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination of passing the seed through the fire to <hi>Moleck.</hi> the 22. forbids <hi>Sodomy:</hi> the 23. forbids the Carnall knowledge of any beast, &amp;c. these severall and distinct offences onely, we take to be the genuine sense of this Chapter, and that the forbidding of mariage cannot rightly be grounded from this place; but that the <hi>Papacy</hi> since it fell from integrity made use of it for <hi>Lucre</hi> as is amply declared in the first part; and this we are induced to thinke, not onely by the practise and custome, before the law to marry and raise up seed with their next of kindred, which we need not here repeate, because it is so largely set forth in little <hi>Nonsuch:</hi> for except Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> can confute all those places there cited before,<note place="margin">☞</note> and after the Law, and shew us by other places of <hi>Scripture</hi> they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother meaning, he hath said nothing in his <hi>Animadversion</hi> worthy of regard, it rather seemes a Ridiculous <hi>Aversion</hi> from the truth: and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that this 18. Chapter of <hi>Levit.</hi> hath no meaning of marriage will appeare to them that are not wilfully partiall, in the 20. Chapter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which appoints the punishment to such as transgresse these commands,<note place="margin">☞</note> and begins with the latter part, He that gives his seed to <hi>Moleck</hi> shall be stoned; the man that commits <hi>Adultery</hi> with another mans wife the <hi>Adulterer</hi> and the <hi>Adulteresse</hi> shall be put to death, then he that lies with his fathers wife, and he that lies with his daughter in Law, and if a man lye with mankinde, and if a man take a woman and her daughter, and if a man or a woman lie with a beast, and if a man take his sister and uncover her nakednesse, these are to be punished with death, we give you but the Abstract, onely he concludes this point, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:160389:6"/> if a man uncovers the nakednesse of his brothers wife they shall dye Childlesse; which with the rest, do h fully fortifie our opinions touching the distinction we have made already, betwixt uncovering shame, or nakednesse, and marriage,<note place="margin">☞</note> for here's not a word of marrying you see, but of <hi>Adultery,</hi> uncovering nakednesse, lying carnally, &amp;c. then shall we thinke that <hi>Abraham</hi> who tooke his Sister to wife, or he that is commanded in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> to marry his brothers wife, deserved this punishment, surely no man of reason will say so; shall that holy estate be ranged in punishment with <hi>Adultery, Buggery,</hi> and <hi>Sodomy?</hi> God forbid: Then here in this 20. Chapter you see plainly if you please, what is meant by uncovering of nakednesse in the 18.<note place="margin">☞</note> Chapter former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cited; that is the man that lies carnally with his Fathers wife, it doth not say one that married his Fathers wife after his decease, but he that lies with his Fathers wife,<note place="margin">1 Of Cor. c. 5.</note> which is to be understood in his life time (or after not being married, and that is the fornication Saint <hi>Paul</hi> speakes of a fornication that was not committed among the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> And the man is meant also that lyes with his Sister as <hi>Amnon</hi> did with <hi>Tamer,</hi> and would not aske her of her Father for a wife; this is the uncovering of nakednesse that ought to be punished among the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said abominations, and not the marriage of single people though they be of nearest kindred; for if that had been the Law <hi>Tamer</hi> would not have desired her Brother <hi>Amnon</hi> to aske her for a wife, and so have been guilty of her own death; but she knew marriage was safe and lawfull,<note place="margin">☞</note> and the fornication onely (in such degrees, so worthy of punishment, and of her so much detested. Are you satisfied yet Mr. <hi>Edwards?</hi> if not we will give you one gradation more, that we suppose will satisfie the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Reader: in the 18. Chapter alleadged we have the <hi>prohibition,</hi> in the 20. the <hi>punishment,</hi> and if you peruse the 27. you shall also finde the <hi>Curse,</hi> we will recite it in order, beginning at the 15. vers. <hi>Cursed be the man that maketh any graven or molten Image; Cursed be he that setteth light by his Father or Mother; cursed be he that removeth his neighbours land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke; cursed be he that maketh the blind to wander out of his way; cursed be he that perverteth the judgement of the stranger, or Fatherlesse; cursed be he that lyeth with his Fathers wife because he uncovereth his Fathers skirt; cursed be he that lyeth with any manner of beast, cursed be he that lyeth with his Sister; cursed be he that lyeth with his Mother in law; cursed be he that smiteth his neighbour secretly; cursed be he that taketh reward to slay an innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, &amp;c.</hi> will you include the holy state of <hi>Marriage</hi> amongst these curses who will beleive you? though we like not <hi>tautoligies,</hi> we cannot too often, (against this <hi>Popish</hi> yoake) remember the case of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of <hi>Iudah,</hi> of the brother in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> of <hi>Boaz,</hi> of <hi>Tamar,</hi> of the seven Brothers in the <hi>Gospell,</hi> withall the rest cited in the first and second part of this Treatise, which like unto so many linkes in a Golden Chaine do strengthen and confirme each other; then note the lying with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:160389:7"/> wife, and uncovering his skirt mentioned amongst these curses in the 20. v. note also the 21. that speakes of lying with any manner of beast, the 22. of lying with the Sister, so that these emergent trespasses in kindred hedging in (as it were of both sides) the abomination of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with any manner of beast,<note place="margin">☞</note> and therefore must of necessity be meant of the highest degree of fornication committed with the Wife in the Fathers life time, and with the Sister without marriage: and such is the uncovering nakednesse or shame in the 18. of <hi>Levit.</hi> for where marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is spoke of indeed (as it is in so many other parts of the old and new Testament needlesse to rehearse, it is called in plaine and direct termes <hi>Marriage,</hi> admitting of no other attribute, be it with kindred or strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. If the Adder will be deafe, the Charmer loseth his labour; some are infatuated with a blinde zeale without knowledge; some by an old custome (though evill in it selfe) not considering whether or no it was fi st introduced by an overruling power for covetous and <hi>Monopolizing</hi> ends; but to such as are of a cleare impartiall minde indued with sense and reason, the least of these plaine and manifest <hi>Scripture</hi> proofes will be sufficient.</p>
               <p>In this place wee would take a little leave to let you know how M. <hi>Edwards</hi> in his <hi>Animadversions</hi> of this Head doth ingenuously give un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of nakednesse the same interpretation that wee do, saying a man may not uncover the nakednesse,<note place="margin">☞</note> that is, commit fornication with those that are remotest in bloud; and wee say much lesse with those that are the nearest: And now hee hath given it the proper sense, which is fornication, wee hope hee will no more call it Marriage: but what hee meanes by his story of Womens <hi>flowers,</hi> we do not well know except it be to make children wonder as hee himselfe doth to see a question or quere asked in Print: yet after all, if M. <hi>Edwards</hi> can snew us by the Originall in <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> that approaching to kindred to uncover their nakednesse (which you see himselfe sayes is fornication) or uncovering of shame and Marriage to have one and the same signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and so to be understood in this <hi>Chapter</hi> against all other <hi>Texts</hi> before and after the Law he saith something; but we do more then sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose that in the <hi>Originall</hi> this uncovering of nakednesse will appeare to be committing of shame by fornication having no relation at all to marriage, more then the papish skill to <hi>insnare</hi> for fees: therefore his first place of <hi>Scripture</hi> hee boasts of, hath made against him and leaves him like a <hi>Collier</hi> grim'd with his own coles.</p>
               <p>Next let us examine his other <hi>Scripture</hi> in the new <hi>Testament,</hi> where <hi>Iohn</hi> reproved <hi>Herod</hi> for taking his Brother <hi>Phillips</hi> Wife; this hee sayeth cannot bee evaded by saying hee tooke her by force and lived in fornication, for the Text sayeth hee had married her; no truly M. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,</hi> we will not go about to evade it that way but wee will shortly tell you how wee will evade it and justly too; and though wee say of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:160389:7"/>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> as hee himselfe sayd of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> wee are not worthy to undoe his shoe latchet, nor presume of the least glimpse of his <hi>spirit;</hi> yet we are not altogether so unlearn'd, or ignorant in humane knowledge, but we can condemne this fact of <hi>Herods</hi> as exceeding all example; for wee never reade that the very <hi>Heathen</hi> thought it lawfull to take away another mans Wife from him in his life time; and though wee reade that <hi>David</hi> committed <hi>adultery</hi> with <hi>B<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rsheba,</hi> and was a King as <hi>Herod</hi> was, yet hee did not take her away to himselfe till <hi>Ʋriah</hi> was dead: now M <hi>Edwards</hi> may please to know that when <hi>Herod</hi> married <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias,</hi> his Bother <hi>Phillip</hi> (her lawfull husband) was then living; for they were contemporaries, so saith <hi>Iosephus</hi> their great and learned <hi>Antiquary,</hi> and some others curious in the search of such things say that <hi>Phillip</hi> out lived his Brother <hi>Herod</hi> (who wee know, died of a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some disease) they say also that <hi>Herods</hi> lawfull Wife <hi>Mariamne</hi> was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at the same time, and after her <hi>repudiation</hi> built that stately <hi>fabrick</hi> called <hi>Miriams</hi> Tower, which shewes as yet some ruins to this day in the place where old <hi>Ierusalem</hi> stood, for all Travellers agree, that the new Town which now is, takes in very little of that which was distroyed by <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Vespatian:</hi> but what need other Authors seeing the <hi>Scripture</hi> it selfe makes it plaine, for in the 3. of St. <hi>Luke</hi> the 1. <hi>v</hi> (and in <hi>Iohns</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistery) we reade that as <hi>Herod</hi> was <hi>Tetrarck</hi> of <hi>Galile</hi> his Brother <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> was also <hi>Tetrarch</hi> of <hi>Iturea</hi> and the Region of <hi>Trachonitis,</hi> and in the 19 and 20 verse of the very same Chapter wee reade that <hi>Herod</hi> being reproved for <hi>Herodias</hi> his brother <hi>Philips</hi> Wife and other evills, yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one more, which was the putting of <hi>Iohn</hi> in prison; so you see at that instant they were both <hi>Tetrarches</hi> of severall <hi>Provinces,</hi> Therefore as touching this his second proofe how absurd it is, let the Reader judge; If the <hi>popes</hi> champions can fence no better wee shall easily give two hits for one: but to our businesse you see M. <hi>Edwards</hi> both by our first and latter discourse that we detest Fornication and Adultery more then you or any other can do that speaks or writes against the marriage of single people, and wee are so far from excusing this act of <hi>Herods,</hi> that we think it worthy of the punishment mentioned in the 20 of <hi>Leuit</hi> awarded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Adulterers, Buggerers, Sodomites,</hi> and such as defile themselves with beasts, or lie carnally with their nearest Kindred to uncover thier shame and nakednesse, which we,<note place="margin">☜</note> and so doth M. <hi>Edwards</hi> you see by chance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret fornication: but to think the holy ordinance of marriage it selfe deserves such punishment in the next Kindred that are single were great impiety, for that is a duty commanded often enough proved in the first part: neither are wee taught that simple fornication in them that were <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot of Kin was to be punished with death, but the parties were to make amends by Marriage as appeares in <hi>Deut.</hi> Chap. 22. Ve. 29. Where if a man lie with a Damsell that is not betroth'd, hee shall give unto the Damsells Father fifty <hi>shekells</hi> of Silver, and after take her to Wife; and in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:160389:8"/> the 19 Chap. of <hi>Levit.</hi> v. 20. Whosoever lieth carnally with a bondmayd, shee shall be scourg'd they shall not be put to death, &amp;c. then the case of the <hi>Midianites,</hi> Numb. 31. and the <hi>Levite;</hi> Judges the 19 mentioned in little <hi>Non-such,</hi> so that if there were no tolleration for simple fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on yet we see there was a connivency upon such and such penalties, but in Kindred within such a degree, it was punishable (and worthily too) with <hi>Adultery</hi> and other abominations formerly rehearsed; but what is all this to marriage with Kindred or strangers, which differs as much from all sorts of fornication as the East is from the West, surely that holy order can never come in question amongst these other enormities without grosse and couetous <hi>popery</hi> rightly taxed in little <hi>Non-such,</hi> and sufficiently opened both there and in this discourse; for shall we thinke that marriage with Kindred deserves greater punishment then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication aforesaid, if there were not so many <hi>Texts</hi> in <hi>Scripture</hi> that cals it holy, and so many other that commands the next Kinsman to doe that duty; yet it were against common reason, and the punishing of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences is plaine <hi>morality</hi> within the compasse of our reason, it is no <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery</hi> to Rack our beliefe;<note place="margin">☞</note> So then fornication is a great offence, but we say it is the worst and highest in Kindred &amp; deserves the greater punishment, because it is more unnaturall to abuse Kinsfolk then strangers; And now to conclude this point of <hi>Herod,</hi> the <hi>Text</hi> doth not say hee married one that had beene h<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s brothers VVife, but one that was his brothers Wife, that is, at that time; Therefore <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> worthily reproved him which makes nothing at all to M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his purpose, for if his brother <hi>Phillip</hi> had been dead, and his own Wife <hi>Miriamne,</hi> hee might lavvfully have married her according to their Jewish custome, and according to the <hi>Text</hi> in <hi>Deuterenomy</hi> as touching marriage with the brothers Wife: And that this is cleare as the day appeares in the 22 of <hi>Matthew,</hi> 12 of <hi>Mark,</hi> 20 of <hi>Luke,</hi> where the question is put to our <hi>Saviour</hi> touching the seven brothers that married successively one woman; if it had not been the custome and lawfull, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur <hi>Saviour</hi> would have reproved it, as hee did the 10th of <hi>Marke</hi> in case of <hi>divorce:</hi> wee know also our King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight did (very little beyond memory) marry his deceased brothers wife, if it were not lawfull why did our <hi>Clergy</hi> consent unto it? you say he had the <hi>popes</hi> dispensation,<note place="margin">☞</note> oh had he so? hee would also have had that to have put her avvay, and no doubt but hee might have obtained it too (for money) had not the wyly father been affraid of the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the Fift, who was her brother: but yet it would not serve the turne, his conscience moved him so, we rather thinke it vvas his <hi>concupiscence;</hi> However there vvas packt some of his own <hi>Clergy</hi> and some in <hi>France</hi> that gave their verdit for him: Though othersome of the most pious and most learned<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Tho. Moore.</note> chose to lose their heads rather then consent: And how then, there was no such Kindred betwixt him and his next Wives to move his conscience, yet when his appetite served hee could finde a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:160389:8"/> ready vvay to chop off their heads, for to sue a divorce was too tedious: but we know that learned Knight S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> sayes in his Pres<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e he was the only exact patterne of a mercilesse and <hi>tiranicall</hi> Prince, therefore hee can be no president for us to put away, or refuse our Wives that are of Kin to us. Neither have M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his two <hi>Scriptures,</hi> he boasts of, confuted our opinion, but (with the rest we have here cited) much confirmed and strengthened it: And though we detest and abhor Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Adultery in all kinde of persons (but chiefely in Kindred) as much as M. <hi>Edwards</hi> or any one living; yet now wee (more then ever) avouch the holy estate of Marriage to be both commanded and the custome with the nearest Kindred as well after the 18 of <hi>Leviticus</hi> as before, even unto the time of the <hi>Gospell:</hi> as appeares in the case of the seaven Brothers formerly mentioned: It skils not much whether <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodias</hi> lately in our Discourse, was sister to <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Phillip</hi> as some sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose by the name: It was in custome amongst the <hi>Romans</hi> to use those appellations as <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ias</hi> the Brother, and <hi>Livia</hi> the Sister, <hi>Tullius</hi> and <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, Octavius</hi> and <hi>Octavia,</hi> &amp;c. and what is in fashion at Court, you know, will shortly come into the Country, for <hi>Herod</hi> was a <hi>Roman Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch,</hi> therefore this conjecture is probable; and if it were so, <hi>Herod</hi> was not reproved for Kindred sake, but for taking another mans Wife, and in that case <hi>John Baptist</hi> would have done no lesse if <hi>Phillip</hi> had not beene his brother; but setting these and many other apart that might be alledged to prove the custome, for a closing instance, wee say that <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of <hi>Jesus</hi> our blessed <hi>Saviour,</hi> were of a <hi>Tribe</hi> and Kindred as appeares by their <hi>Geneologies</hi> in the Gospell of St. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> and St. <hi>Luke;</hi> neither hath this prohibition, as we shall shew here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, any longer Pedegree then from such as (for gaine and lucre) hath tollerated Stewes and Ribaldry: for seeing S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes Marriage is honorable in all without exception, as is set forth at large in the first part, wee say that repudiating Wives (except in case of <hi>Adultery</hi>) and forbidding of Marriage is flatly the Doctrine of Devills: observe the <hi>Apostle</hi> here in this<note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.3.</note> Chapter, sayeth this forbidding should be in the latter times; Therefore M. <hi>Edwards</hi> forgets himselfe much to ci e <hi>Leviticus,</hi> which was in the first times, therefore not then to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden; and wee are forgetfull also to trouble you twice with one ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for by what you have formerly reade you may gather how hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters that <hi>Chapter</hi> after the <hi>p<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pes</hi> Grammer: and now because M. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> in this last <hi>Animadversion,</hi> speakes three times of <hi>incestuous</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, without giving us a definition what incest is, and sayes he hath (out of one County) the names of three <hi>Independents</hi> that have married <hi>incestuously:</hi> by this you see, hee is a <hi>champion</hi> indeed, and hath his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences to agravate his quarrell: yet seeing hee will not take the paines let us indeavour to give a definition to this <hi>Bugbeare,</hi> that these <hi>Independents</hi> (as he cals them because they have married with their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:160389:9"/> Kindred may have the better satisfaction: first wee would aske M. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> how and from whence hee derives his so often Iterated word <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cest:</hi> If hee will not tell us, then wee aske counsell of the <hi>Grammarians,</hi> whom wee take to be impartiall <hi>expositors;</hi> if it be from the verbe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesto,</hi> that they render to pollute and defile also to defile by reason of a dead body: if it be from <hi>incestus</hi> the adjective that they render pollut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, defiled, <hi>unchast,</hi> and <hi>whorish:</hi> if it be from <hi>Incestus</hi> the substantive, that they likewise render <hi>lechery</hi> committed with one that is nigh a kin to him that committeth it; also all manner of pollution: now M. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> is not here the matter decided, which wee have debated in the first and second part, here is the word <hi>Incest</hi> derived and designed which is to pollute or defile, to be unchast or <hi>whorish,</hi> to commit <hi>lechery</hi> with one that is nigh a kin; I hope you will not say there is either <hi>pollution,</hi> or <hi>whordom,</hi> or <hi>lechery</hi> in holy Wedlock; Then is not this the same that we say <hi>Incestuous</hi> Fornication, or <hi>incestuous</hi> lechery if you will, but for <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestuous</hi> Marriage that smels of the Pumpe (of the <hi>pope</hi> and his champion wee should have said) wee have told you and proved it often to be a <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish glosse</hi> for their profit, so we finde it and so we leave it; And for these three <hi>Independents</hi> you speak of that have married their near Kinswomen, if there be three score of them, we suppose they will not love their Wives the lesse for your aspersion, but much dearer, because it is presumed they have married without any covetous ends according to the first and best institution: but M <hi>Edwards</hi> perhaps (like blind <hi>Homer</hi>) can write well of none that crosses his humor. Lastly, for perclose we here intend to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuse you because you have abused your selfe, to take us for <hi>Independents</hi> that makes this defence; we do assure you we are none such, if you mean that they are <hi>Independents</hi> which put down <hi>Bishops</hi> we disclaime the title, for wee approve their <hi>function</hi> though tis many yeares since we disliked their <hi>jurisdiction</hi> and their Lordships, yet if a man have a lame Leg wee had rather cure him then cut off his head: And if you call those <hi>Ind pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> that would have no King or Government in Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth,<note place="margin">☞</note> we disclaime that too, for wee would have both, knowing that God is the God of order and not of confusion, wee further agnize our selves to be some of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> protestants detesting supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>popery,</hi> and also much abominating these <hi>colophantick</hi> Sects and Seismes that have imbroyled our three Kingdoms; but if we be averse to such as terrify the conscience that (by their own covetous and beggerly Rudiments) would restraine us from that Christian liberty the <hi>Gospell</hi> allows us,<note place="margin">☞</note> so far, we in depend, And desire the reversion of Romish dregs (vvith all new <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Scism's</hi>) may be purged away: As touching this forbidding of Marriage, we have sufficiently already, and may move amp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hereafter prove it to be a <hi>popish</hi> Relique; then seeing you will have no <hi>Bishops,</hi> vve desire such Lawes and <hi>cannons</hi> as vvere made in the time of Superstition, and continued by them, may be burnt and imbezeld, because
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:160389:9"/> they have most impiously served not onely to punish, but also to take away the lives of devout Christians,<note place="margin">☜</note> and also to divide bodies vvhose hearts vvere rightly united, and such as God hath commanded that no man should put asunder. And in regard you say you have struck off the head of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> let us desire you to cut of the <hi>Tayle</hi> too, and vvee vvill be all friends. Now M. <hi>Edwards</hi> because you say you are large in your <hi>Aversion,</hi> vve therefore say vve have bin the larger in our <hi>observation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The rest of the third Book of</hi> Gangrena <hi>wee have not perused, nor did we greatly thinke it worth our labour; onely we accident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally saw a little</hi> Pamphlet <hi>formerly named, that sayes you write perniciously even to the taking away (if it were in your power) the lives of such as onely desire as they professe, the freedome of a good conscience, with the ancient lawes and liberties of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive county.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this be so it is not vvell; vve ought to reforme one another in the Spirit of meeknesse, and not vvith revilings and threatnings: but not to medle beyond our ovvn matter, vve conclude your <hi>Animadvesions</hi> to be me<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re temporisers from vvhence vve can gather neither Wit, Learning, or Instruction, and so vve give you the <hi>Bonus noctius,</hi> leaving you and your other <hi>Antagonists</hi> to decide your other differences.</p>
               <p>And now a little discourse to such as have married their neare kins-Women, vve knovv there is a <hi>popish</hi> injunction that forbids marriage in such and such degrees, and great penalties devised by the Civill Lavv, vvhich have no other ground but from the <hi>popish Cannons:</hi> Then hovv muffled in error have vvee beene in these latter times, to maintaine such opinions and yet vvith all (till novv of late) believe the <hi>pope</hi> had povver (for his profit) to dispence with what degree he pleased: but above all observe the ridiculous reasons that some alledge to uphold that dive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Doctrine, for so it is call'd in the Text: And indeed one Author sayth truly, within some short time after the Apostles, It behoved there should be great stupidity and blindnesse, else how should <hi>Antichristian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>isme</hi> be introduced to the full, as since it hath been; but to returne and aquaint you with one of the aforesaid Reasons some alledge <hi>Aristotle,</hi> a heathen Philosopher, that in his 9 History <hi>Animar.</hi> Chap. 47. tells you a tale of a Camell that kil'd his keeper for suffering him to couple with his dam, and another of a horse that likewise served his Dam, and after ran to the Sea and lept from a Rock into it: behold here what shall we thinke of <hi>Authors</hi> that cite such matters to men that have reason? as if beasts that have no reason were to be our presidents for our life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation; for what man that hath so much wit as <hi>Camell, Horse</hi> or <hi>Asse</hi> can believe that the foresaid accidents happened thorough the causes speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as if there was never <hi>Camell</hi> before or since, that kil'd a man, or horse
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:160389:10"/> that drowned himselfe, who is it amongst us that hath kept a breed of Cattell, Sheepe, or studd of horses and Mares? but the males in their seasons, have intermixt with the females promiscuously; and have wee not often received losse in our said goods many severall wayes, and our servants hurt and sometimes kil'd by horse and beasts? What then? shall we attribute those accidents to the mixture of our beasts in their severall kinds? or shall we esteeme them uncleane and not feede upon them? if we do we shall loose our reason, and surely become more brutish then they; but what impression can not any fable make where the reasonable part is set aside, and ignorance become the Mother of devotion? It is the <hi>Popes purgatory</hi> pickpurse that hath broach'd a hundred of these impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures; for the reasonable part of this Argument against marriage in kindred, hath no better emphasis or grace then if a man should say, I have as good provision (of all kinds) at home, as I can finde in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, but yet it doth not like me, Therefore I wil seek further to please my appetite; how then? will you approve of his judgement that will leave his own cates, which hee knoweth to be good and wholesome, to buy abroad that which may be corrupt and deceitfull, as often times it proves? Even so have wee better cause and opportunity to know the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and qualities of our nearest Kindred then of strangers; Therefore seeing wee finde in <hi>Scripture,</hi> it was the practise of the <hi>Patriarkes</hi> and our forefathers to chuse their Wives out of their owne stock, and was with all (before and after the Law, a duty commanded; (we do not say but since the Gospell there is a Christian liberty) yet if such liking happen now amongst the nearest of kin without any lustfull desire, but onely for <hi>propagation</hi> and reall intent of marriage, vve see no cause why any (that have not lost their sense) should give credit to heathen fables or seeke to pope for a dispensation.</p>
               <p>Another reason there is alledg'd and that by one that would be thought a great <hi>Doctor:</hi> A man of great Reading no doubt hee vvas and able to cite many Authors; but we have a saying the greatest Clerks are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the wisest men; And wee know there are divers who have writ great Volums, and yet had not the true genuine sence of matters, nor a right interpretation; but let us see what weight the reason hath which hee brings against this nearnesse of kindred: That it is not lawfull sayeth hee,<note place="margin">☞</note> to marry ones Sister doth appeare by <hi>Abrahams</hi> denying <hi>Sarah</hi> to bee his Wife amongst the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> but sayed shee was his sister: observe well this passage was not this to save his life? reade his Story and you will finde them his owne words; for shee might have beene his sister and not his Wife, and then it had beene no offence to him if another had taken her in marriage; but being his sister, and his Wife also the case was far otherwayes, for then hee feared they might have killed him to have had her free to themselves, because it was not lawfull amongst the most barbarous heathen to take another mans Wife:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:160389:10"/> And now marke with all the same answer of <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Abimelech</hi> in his returne, <hi>viz.</hi> She was his sister, and yet afterwards when <hi>Abimeleck</hi> knew shee was his Wife, and blam'd him for conce aling it, <hi>Abraham</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied he thought the feare of God was not in that place, and that they would have kil'd him for her (the Text sayeth shee was a faire Woman) yet he had not wholy d ssembled, for she was his sister the Daughter of his Father and so became his Wife. Therefore it is lawfull (by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) to marry the Sister;<note place="margin">☜</note> so the reason that this <hi>Doctor</hi> brings makes just point blank against himselfe: And here we would aske him how the World was peopled after the Creation, and after the <hi>deluge;</hi> was it not by the issue of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Noe</hi> (that is) by naturall brothers and sisters? Oh, but you will say, then there was a necessi y, and we say there is no necessity to do that which is unlawfull, and if it were lawfull then; the reasons and circumstances of these times makes it lawfull now; for where so many Families of best integrity are rooted out of their Cuntry by wicked <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Scisms,</hi> together with a most inhumane and an unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall civill War, and thereby forced to seeke habitation amongst the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then in unplanted Countries, why should not they propagate in their tribes as our fore-fathres did: of this opinion are some <hi>Doctors</hi> most ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute, well known to us for piety and learning:<note place="margin">☜</note> but what will not some other <hi>Doctors</hi> doe? when <hi>popery</hi> is in request they have reasons for that: when the <hi>Presbytery</hi> Carries it, then that is highly extol'd; when the <hi>Jndependency</hi> hath sway, that must be desended too: was it not well prayed of him that desired to keep his soule from a <hi>Church-man,</hi> his body from a <hi>Physitian,</hi> and his Estate from the <hi>Lawyer:</hi> but doe not these things give occasion of scandall to our Christian Religion even amongst the <hi>beathen?</hi> God grant that our errors may be errors of ignorance rather then of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption or against conscience; and that we do not with some straine a Gnat and swallow a Camell; such as would deny this primitive ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance as touching Marriage (wherein there can be no prejudice if parties be single, and their intentions reall) and yet admit of grosse superstition in <hi>popery</hi> with other <hi>Hereticall Sects</hi> and <hi>Scismes</hi> also, which hath opened so wide a gap to all impiety.</p>
               <p>Wee must not forget another reason that some alledge against this nearnesse of kindred, that is, they have known many mischances happen to such; so have we known many blessings powred upon such; and doth all other matches thrive that are not of Kin? This reason is as like the fire as ere it may look; either it comes from an old Wife, a young novice, or the <hi>popes</hi> broker; for what is this to say, but if you marry your Kindred (without the <hi>popes</hi> licence) you can never thrive; this is a great scarcrow to the covetous, and hath so infatuated the debauch'd and simple sort, that they had rather commit fornication with twenty strange Women then live in holy Wedlock with one of their Kindred. But leaving this as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthy of regard or further answer, one thing more we would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:160389:11"/> unto such as M. <hi>Edwards</hi> cals <hi>Jndependents</hi> for marrying with their Kindred, and in their tribes, namely the time about which this divelish Doctrine (of forbidding marriage) came into these Western Islands; and also who they were that set it abroach; but because we wil forge nothing of our own braines we will cite you a warrantable Record. We read that in the year 1172 <hi>Christianus</hi> the <hi>popes</hi> Legate, <hi>Donatus, Lawreance,</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicus Archbishops</hi> with their Suffragan <hi>Bishops, Abbots, Priors, Deanes,</hi> and <hi>Archdeacons</hi> with many Prelates, &amp;c. These sayth the Irish Chronicle kept a Synod at <hi>Cashell,</hi> debated many matters, made sundry Statutes and wholesome Lawes; <hi>viz.</hi> that people should refraine to marry with their nearest kinsfolks; that children should be Catechiz'd without the Church doore, Baptized in the Font, &amp;c. That every one should pay their Tythes of Cattle, Corne and all other encrease, faithfully to the <hi>Church:</hi> that <hi>Church lands</hi> should be free from all other exactions of Lords, Noblemen, &amp;c. no <hi>cuddies cosheries, coigne</hi> &amp; <hi>livery</hi> to be within the <hi>Church</hi> territories: when any <hi>Earick</hi> or cutting lay upon the people for murder, or head money, no person of the <hi>Clergy</hi> (though they were a kin to the murderer) should contribute anything but all to lie upon the Laiety; That any person dying should give the third part of his substance for the oversight and performance of his Will; Now you must imagin that charge will fall to Sr. <hi>John</hi> our Parish Priest, brother Monke, or fryer, &amp;c. This is sufficient to let you know of what nature these Lawes were of, and to whom they were wholesome: The Clergy you see were very kinde to themselves; but perhaps the Layety (that must beare all the burden) had little reason to thinke them either wholesome or tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some; seldome shall you see them make any Lawes against their profi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; neither was their prohibition in matter of Marriage the least accession thereunto. Their <hi>dispensations</hi> mentioned in the first part have beene well payed for; yet to forbid the Banes with one hand and to joyne them together with the other for money, what thinke you, is it not <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus pocus?</hi> who is it but knowes it a lawfull Ordinance, or else that it cannot be made so for money; well then, the time these lawes were made is here to be observed 1172. And by whom? but by such Law mongers as Tolerate <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Stewes</hi> for annuall Rents: Then was it not neare the time that the <hi>Bishops</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> usurpt the title of Universality, though some of themselves rebuked <hi>John Bishop</hi> of <hi>Constantinople</hi> for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting the same. I suppose it was, and from which time forwards their <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> their selling of pardons, their giving of Kingdoms, their Buls and Excomunications with many devises besides have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyled all Christendome. It is further to be observ'd that <hi>Jreland</hi> did flourish in learning and piety: And it is needlesse here to recite the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lives of <hi>Patricius,</hi> his contemporaries and successors, seeing their <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story</hi> is so frequent, except wee could have found this prohibition in their time, which nowhere we read of: Then are we confident it hath
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:160389:11"/> no elder birth then the times aforesaid, when all corruption, bribery, and symony crept into the <hi>Arch prelacy.</hi> And now if it be granted that the foresaid marriages in the next of kindred be lawfull (for so we take it till we be convinc'd by Scripture, and that expounded without temporising, partiality, or private interest) then it may be demanded what inconvenience there is in it, except some will say you doe not wisely to stand upon the fi st ordinance to the prejudice of your estate; that is, to take your Kins-woman with nothing when you might have a stranger with money: wee doe not reade that <hi>Abraham</hi> had either, Lands, or Goods with his Wife and sister <hi>Sara;</hi> or <hi>Jsack</hi> with <hi>Rebecca,</hi> but sent presents to obtaine her; or yet <hi>Jacob</hi> with his Wives, but ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved two prentiships for them: of M rriages made for encroaching and covetous ends (and Lawes made against it even by the very <hi>Heathen</hi>) there is enough sayed in the first part: for wee finde that marriage was ordained to <hi>propagate</hi> and multiply Man-kinde, and not to beget money; So then the kindred being agreed according to the first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, and intire affection, the inconvenience is none amongst them: whereas in other covetous matches there is frequent quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling: as in the <hi>Clandestine</hi> and stolne Marriages, what suits and troubles ariseth; And also in others fashion'd by compact in case of not performing <hi>joynture</hi> one the one side and detayning portion on the other, which begets perpetuall brauling, and not seldome doe they mistake the way to one anothers bed; whereas to th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynings proceeding from that conscionable duty injoyn'd to the next kinsman (and where naturall affection invites) all such jarrs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelies are avoyded. Then wee cannot too often reiterate the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetousnesse of the <hi>pope,</hi> and his Clergy (with other secular Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates who have dranke too deepe of that Babylonish cuppe) in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lawes to prohibit so just an ordinance, and yet (for money) dispense with their owne edicts. Therefore wee concurre in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him that sayeth<note n="*" place="margin">Ʋlpian.</note> an unlawfull custome ought not to bee binding, neither can course of time mend that which was naught from the beginning; for what it not grounded upon good right is not made good by continuance:<note place="margin">☜</note> observe that <hi>Augustine</hi> also in his Booke <hi>de vera Religione,</hi> Cap. 31. <hi>mihi lex esse non videtur quae justa non est,</hi> it seemes to mee sayeth hee to bee no Law at all which is not just: And how contrary these humane injunctions are to Divine Ordinance, is elegantly proved in the first part (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled Little <hi>Non-such</hi>) if what you reade here bee short of your expectation.</p>
               <p>As touching the most famous of the <hi>Heathen</hi> (which History Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords unto us for Armes and learning) who Married in the very nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest degrees; as <hi>Cyrus, Antiochus, Ptolomy</hi> and so many more, which to recite were to goe on <hi>ad infinitum;</hi> neither neede wee them for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:160389:12"/> president, having (in <hi>Scripture</hi>) so many of the fathers and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks:</hi> onely this wee mention to shew the practise and custome both wi h <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> (for ought wee know) till the VVorld was old five thousand Yeares and upwards, for untill the Yeare 1172 for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly mentioned, wee have not read of any such prohibition; If any doe informe us better, wee shall not bee deafe to understand it, and then you perceive from whence it came; to helpe your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, wee once more tell you from the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Clergy</hi> who (for money, will dispense neverthelesse and tolerate <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Stewes</hi> to boote; what <hi>Martyrs massacrees</hi> and blood-shed their Lawes, <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> and inquisition with their other plots and practises, have made since that time in Christendome, wee suppose is yet fresh in your memory: Therefore wee wonder not as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> doth at his shaddow, when hee speakes of pleading for an <hi>Heresy</hi> in Print, whereas (you see) it is no other then a bare question, but wee wonder the <hi>Pope</hi> should finde Champions to plead in Print (for his fees and extortion) against the holy institution of Marriage; for wee can discerne no other fource or Fountaine from whence that divelish Doctrine proceedes: now if any can shew us wherein wee are mistaken, they shall perceive wee are not impetuously obstinate, provided alwayes they take the Scripture for their guide; for as one sayeth <hi>Diamonds</hi> can onely cut <hi>Diamonds;</hi> and no such Comments on the <hi>Scripture</hi> as the <hi>Scripture</hi> it selfe: Then if severall Texts of the old and new Testament, cited here and in the little <hi>Non such,</hi> touching Marriage, the practise and example of the Fathers before and after the Law, hee refuted with so many other Texts equivalent and interpreted without partiality, wee are satisfyed; else the <hi>popish Cannons</hi> and <hi>Heathen</hi> fables, do not affright us, but gives us cause to detest their impiety.</p>
               <p>Lastly, for perclose to such as inveigle their kindred and make them <hi>concubines,</hi> or commit Fornication with them, wee wish the punishment allotted in the 20. of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> to them and the like capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall offenders: But such as doe really (and with their good liking) make them their Wives according to the holy Ordinance, wee pray for, and wish them the blessings of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah, Isack</hi> and <hi>Rebecca,</hi> with the rest of the Fathers and <hi>Patriarches</hi> which Married in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: for where there is neither Covetousnesse, Ambition, or sensuality but onely motives in conscience to performe the Kinsmans part (to use the words of <hi>Boas</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruth.</hi> ca. vers. 13.</note> to <hi>Ruth</hi>) out of a duty commanded; no doubt but God will accept the good intention and give it a blessing accordingly.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:160389:12"/>
            <head>Postcript.</head>
            <p>IF any suppose there are digressions in this discourse that savor, somewhat of the <hi>Satyre:</hi> To the affable and judicous Reader we give this satisfaction: That true it is, M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid phrase did stir up no spleene, but a little just indignation; for by his taxing the questions in little <hi>Non-such</hi> with the words <hi>error, Heresies,</hi> wicked <hi>Pamphlets Incestuous, Independents, &amp;c.</hi> We imagine he was a little <hi>besmeared</hi> with choler or some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else, which made him cleare mistake the matter; for we doe not thinke, under favour, that the asking a Question (with modesty) deserves such Epithetes: (i) <hi>Agrippa</hi> believest thou the <hi>Prophets?</hi> I know thou doest sayeth<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 29. vers. 27.</note> St. <hi>Paul;</hi> he and the rest of the <hi>Apostles</hi> did (as it were) angle for soules by Doctrine and example, not with reviling and threatning; And if any shew us the errors in little <hi>Non-such,</hi> or in this second part (oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned by M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his invective) and will doe it (as our <hi>Saviour</hi> commands) in love and the spirit of meekenesse, found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his tenents upon <hi>Scripture</hi> (as is desired) and with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biassed intention, we will then esteeme him highly, give him great thanks, and heare him gladly.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>